<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Of the infallibilitie of the Chvrch of Rome a discourse written by the Lord Viscount Falkland ...</title>
            <author>Falkland, Lucius Cary, Viscount, 1610?-1643.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40800</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F322</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R40575</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">19368391</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 19368391</idno>
            <idno type="VID">108797</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40800)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 108797)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1669:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Of the infallibilitie of the Chvrch of Rome a discourse written by the Lord Viscount Falkland ...</title>
                  <author>Falkland, Lucius Cary, Viscount, 1610?-1643.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by H. Hall ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCXLV [1645]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Illustrated t.p.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Infallibility.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:108797:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:108797:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>OF THE INFALLIBILITIE OF THE CHVRCH OF ROME. A Diſcourſe written by the Lord Viſcount FALKLAND. Now firſt publiſhed from a Copy of his owne hand.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD,</hi> Printed by <hi>H Hall</hi> Printer to the UNIVERSITY: <hi>M.DC.XLV.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Henry Hall, an arch with two pillars (not in McKerrow)</figDesc>
            </figure>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:108797:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:108797:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>OF THE INFALLIBILI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the Church of ROME.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O him that doubts whether the Church of <hi>Rome have</hi> any errours, they anſwer,<note place="margin">§ 1.</note> that She <hi>hath</hi> none, for She never <hi>can</hi> have any. This being ſo much harder to beleive then the firſt, had need be proved by ſome <hi>certaine</hi> arguments, if they expect that the beleife of this one ſhould draw on whatſoever elſe they pleaſe to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe: Yet this is offered to be proved by no better wayes then thoſe by which <hi>we</hi> offer to prove ſhe <hi>hath erred:</hi> Which are, arguments from <hi>Scripture, Reaſon,</hi> and Ancient Writers; all which, <hi>they</hi> ſay themſelves, are fallible; for nothing is not ſo but the Church; which if it be the onely infallible determinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and that can never be beleived upon <hi>it's owne</hi> authority, we can never <hi>infallibly know</hi> that the Church is infallible: for theſe other wayes of proofe (they ſay) may deceive both them and us; and ſo neither ſide is <hi>bound</hi> to beleive them.</p>
            <p>If they ſay,<note place="margin">§ 2.</note> that an argument out of <hi>Scripture</hi> is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient ground of <hi>Divine faith,</hi> why are they ſo offended with the Proteſtants for beleiving <hi>every part</hi> of <hi>their</hi> Religion upon that ground, upon which they build <hi>all theirs</hi> at once? and if following the ſame Rule with equall deſire of finding the truth by it, (having neither of thoſe qualities, which <hi>Iſidorus Peluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ota</hi> ſayes, are the cauſes of all Hereſies; <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>Prejudication</hi>) why ſhould God be more offended with the one then the other, though they chance to erre?</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:108797:3"/>
            <p>They ſay,<note place="margin">§ 3.</note> the <hi>Church</hi> is therefore made <hi>infallible</hi> by God, that all men may have ſome <hi>certaine</hi> Guide; yet though it <hi>be</hi> infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible, unleſſe it both plainly <hi>appeare</hi> to be ſo, (for it <hi>is</hi> not cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to whom it doth not <hi>appeare</hi> certaine) and unleſſe it be manifeſt <hi>which</hi> is the <hi>Church,</hi> God hath not attained his end; and it were to ſet a Ladder to Heaven and ſeeme to have a great care of my going up, whereas unleſſe there be care taken that I may <hi>know</hi> this Ladder is <hi>here</hi> to that purpoſe, it were as good for me it had never beene ſet.</p>
            <p>If they ſay we <hi>may know</hi> it,<note place="margin">§ 4.</note> for that <hi>Generall</hi> and conſtant <hi>Tradition</hi> inſtructs us in it, I anſwer, that <hi>ignorant</hi> people <hi>cannot know</hi> this, and ſo it can be no Rule for <hi>them;</hi> and if <hi>learned</hi> peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple miſtake in this, there can be no condemnation for <hi>them.</hi> For ſuppoſe to know whether the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> may erre, (as a way which will conclude <hi>againſt</hi> her, but not <hi>for</hi> her; for if She <hi>hath</hi> erred, certainly She <hi>may;</hi> but though ſhe <hi>hath not</hi> erred hitherto, it followes not that She cannot erre,) I ſeeke whether She <hi>have</hi> erred; and conceiving She <hi>hath contradicted</hi> her ſelf, conclude neceſſarily She hath <hi>erred;</hi> I ſuppoſe it not <hi>damnable</hi> though I erre in my judgement: becauſe I try the <hi>Church</hi> by one of thoſe touch-ſtones her ſelf appoints me; which is, <hi>Conformity with the Ancient.</hi> For to ſay I am to beleive the <hi>preſent Church</hi> that it differs not from the former, though it ſeeme to me to doe ſo, is to ſend me to a witneſſe, and bid me not beleive it.</p>
            <p>Now to <hi>ſay</hi> the <hi>Church</hi> is provided for a <hi>Guide</hi> of faith,<note place="margin">§ 5.</note> but muſt be knowne by ſuch markes as the <hi>ignorant</hi> cannot <hi>ſeeke</hi> it by, and the <hi>learned</hi> may chance not to <hi>find</hi> it by, though ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it with all diligence and without all prejudice, can no way ſatisfy me.</p>
            <p>If they ſay,<note place="margin">§ 6.</note> God will <hi>reveale</hi> the truth to whoſoever ſeekes it theſe wayes <hi>ſincerely;</hi> this ſaying <hi>both ſides will</hi> (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out meanes of being confuted) <hi>make uſe of;</hi> therefore it would be as good that <hi>neither did.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When they have proved the <hi>Church</hi> to be <hi>infallible,</hi>
               <note place="margin">§ 7.</note> yet to my underſtanding they have proceeded nothing farther, unleſſe
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:108797:3"/>we can be ſure <hi>which is it;</hi> for it ſignifies onely that God will <hi>allwaies have</hi> a <hi>Church</hi> which ſhall not erre; but not that ſuch or ſuch a <hi>Succeſſiion</hi> ſhall be all waies in the right; not that the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of ſuch a place, and the Clergy that adheres to him ſhall all waies continue in the <hi>true</hi> faith. So that if they ſay the <hi>Greeke</hi> Church is not <hi>the Church,</hi> becauſe by it's owne confeſſion it is <hi>not</hi> infallible; I anſwer, that it may be <hi>now</hi> the <hi>Church,</hi> and may <hi>hereafter</hi> erre, and ſo not be <hi>now</hi> infallible; and yet <hi>the Church never</hi> erre; becauſe before <hi>their</hi> fall from truth, <hi>others</hi> may ariſe to maintaine it, who <hi>then</hi> will be the <hi>Church;</hi> and ſo the <hi>Church</hi> may <hi>ſtill</hi> be infallible; though not in reſpect of any ſet perſons whom we may know at all times for our Guide.</p>
            <p>Then if they prove the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> to be the true <hi>Church,</hi>
               <note place="margin">§ 8.</note> and not the <hi>Greeke, becauſe their</hi> opinions are conſonant either to Scripture or Antiquity, they runne into a circle, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving their <hi>tenets</hi> to be <hi>true,</hi> firſt; becauſe the <hi>Church holds</hi> them &amp; then theirs to be the <hi>true Church,</hi> becauſe it <hi>holds the truth:</hi> which laſt, though it appeare to me the onely way, yet it takes away it's being a Guide which we may follow <hi>without exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,</hi> without which all they ſay beſides is nothing.<note place="margin">§ 9.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Nay ſuppoſe they had evinced, that <hi>ſome Succeſſion</hi> were infallible, and ſo had proved to a <hi>Learned</hi> man that the <hi>Roman Church</hi> muſt be <hi>this,</hi> becauſe none elſe <hi>pretends</hi> to it; yet this can be no ſufficient ground to the <hi>ignorant,</hi> who cannot have any <hi>infallible</hi> foundation for their beleife that the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Greece pretends</hi> not to the ſame; and even to the <hi>Learned</hi> it is but an <hi>accidentall</hi> argument, becauſe if any other company had like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe claimed to be <hi>infallible,</hi> it had overthrowne all ſo proved.</p>
            <p>Nay it is but an <hi>arbitrary</hi> argument,<note place="margin">§ 10.</note> and depends upon the pleaſure of the adverſary; for if any ſociety of Chriſtians would <hi>pretend</hi> to it, the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> could make uſe of it no longer.</p>
            <p>The cheifeſt reaſon why they diſallow of the <hi>Scripture</hi> for <hi>Judge,</hi> is, becauſe when differences ariſe about the <hi>interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> there is no way to end them;<note place="margin">§ 11.</note> and that it will not ſtand with the goodneſſe of God, to damne men for not following
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:108797:4"/>his will, if he had aſſigned no infallible way how to finde it. I confeſſe this to be wonderfull true <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and let them excuſe themſelves that thinke otherwiſe. Yet this will be no argument a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, who beleives that to all who follow their <hi>reaſon</hi> in the <hi>interpretation</hi> of the Scriptures, and ſearch for <hi>Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> God will either give his <hi>grace</hi> for aſſiſtance to <hi>finde</hi> the truth, or his <hi>pardon</hi> if they <hi>miſſe</hi> it: and then this ſuppoſed <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity</hi> of an infallible Guide with this ſuppoſed <hi>damnation</hi> for want of it, fall together to the ground.</p>
            <p>If they command us to beleive <hi>infallibly</hi> the contrary to this,<note place="margin">§ 12.</note> they are to prove it falſe by ſome <hi>infallible</hi> way (for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion muſt be of the ſame nature, and not conclude more then the premiſſes ſet downe,) now ſuch a way, <hi>Scripture</hi> and <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> or <hi>infuſed faith</hi> cannot be (for they uſe to object the <hi>fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libility</hi> of them to thoſe that build their Religion upon them) nor the <hi>Authority</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> for that is part of the queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and muſt be it ſelfe <hi>firſt</hi> proved, and that by none of the former wayes, for the former reaſons.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Popes infallibility</hi> can be no infallible ground of faith,<note place="margin">§ 13.</note> being it ſelfe no <hi>neceſſary</hi> part of the faith (&amp; we can be no ſurer of any thing proved then we are of that which proves it,) and if <hi>he</hi> be fallible, no <hi>part</hi> is the more <hi>infallible</hi> for his ſideing with them. So if the <hi>Church</hi> be divided, I have no way to know which is the <hi>true Church,</hi> but by ſearching which agrees with <hi>Scripture</hi> and <hi>Antiquity,</hi> and ſo judgeing accordingly. (But this is not to ſubmit my ſelfe to her opinions as my <hi>guide,</hi> which they tell us is neceſſary.) Which courſe if they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove not of as a fit one for a <hi>Learned</hi> man, they are in a worſe caſe for the <hi>ignorant,</hi> who can take no courſe at all, nor is the better at all for this Guide, the Church; whileſt two parts diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute <hi>which is it,</hi> and that by arguments he underſtands not.</p>
            <p>If I granted the <hi>Pope,</hi>
               <note place="margin">§ 14.</note> or a <hi>Councell</hi> by him called to be <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible,</hi> yet I conceive their Decrees can be no ſufficient ground (by their own axiomes) of <hi>Divine faith.</hi> For <hi>firſt</hi> (ſay the moſt) No <hi>Councell</hi> is valid not approved by the <hi>Pope</hi> (for
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:108797:4"/>thus they overthrow that held at <hi>Ariminum</hi>) and a <hi>Pope</hi> cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen by <hi>Symony</hi> is <hi>ipſo facto</hi> no Pope. I can then have no cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainer ground for the <hi>infallibility</hi> of thoſe <hi>Decrees,</hi> and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently for my beleife of them, then I have that the choice of him was neither directly nor indirectly <hi>Symoniacall;</hi> which to be certaine of, is abſolutely impoſſible.<note place="margin">§ 15.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> ſuppoſe him <hi>Pope,</hi> and to have <hi>confirmed</hi> the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees;</hi> yet that <hi>theſe are</hi> the Decrees of a Councell, or that he <hi>hath confirmed</hi> them, I can have but an uncontradicted atte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation of many men, (for if another <hi>Councell</hi> ſhould declare <hi>theſe</hi> to have beene the Acts of a <hi>former</hi> Councell, I ſhould neede a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine ſome certaine way of knowing how <hi>this</hi> declaration is a Councels) which is no ground (ſay <hi>they</hi>) of faith, I am ſure not ſo good and generall a one as that Tradition by which we prove that the Scripture is Scripture, which yet they will not allow any to be certaine of but from them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> for the <hi>ſence</hi> of their Decrees,<note place="margin">§ 16.</note> I can have no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter expounder to follow then <hi>Reaſon;</hi> which if, though I mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake, I ſhall not be <hi>damned</hi> for following, why ſhall I for mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaking the ſence of Scripture? Or why am I a leſſe fit interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>one,</hi> then of the <hi>other</hi> were both ſeeme equally cleare? And where they ſeeme ſo (I meane equally cleare) and yet contradictory, ſhall I not as ſoone beleive <hi>Scripture,</hi> which is. without doubt, of at leaſt <hi>as great</hi> authority?</p>
            <p>But I doubt whether <hi>Councells</hi> be fit deciders of Queſtions;<note place="margin">§ 17.</note> for ſuch they cannot be, if they beget more, and men have cauſe to be in greater doubts <hi>afterwards</hi> (none of the <hi>former</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diminiſhed) then they were at firſt.</p>
            <p>Now I conceive there ariſe ſo <hi>many</hi> out of this way,<note place="margin">§ 18.</note> that the Learned cannot end <hi>all</hi> nor the Ignorant know <hi>all.</hi> As beſides the forenamed conſiderations. <hi>Who</hi> is to <hi>call</hi> them, the Pope, or Kings: <hi>Who</hi> are to have <hi>voices</hi> in them; Biſhops only, or Preiſts alſo: <hi>Whether</hi> the <hi>Pope</hi> or <hi>Councell</hi> be <hi>Superiour;</hi> &amp; the <hi>laſt</hi> neede the approbation of the <hi>firſt,</hi> debated among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: <hi>Whether</hi> any Countries not being <hi>called,</hi> or not being there (as the <hi>Abiſſines,</hi> ſo great a part of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> &amp; not reſolvedly
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:108797:5"/>condemend by them for <hi>Heretiques,</hi> were abſent at the Councell of <hi>Trent</hi>) make it not-<hi>generall: Whether</hi> if it be one not every where received (as when the Biſhops ſent from ſome places have exceeded their Commiſſion, as in the Councell of <hi>Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence</hi>) it be yet of neceſſity to be ſubſcribed to: <hi>Whether</hi> there were any <hi>ſurreption</hi> uſed or <hi>force,</hi> and <hi>Whether</hi> thoſe diſanull the Acts: <hi>Whether</hi> the <hi>moſt voyees</hi> are to be held the Act of the <hi>Councell,</hi> or thoſe of <hi>all</hi> are required, (As <hi>Canus</hi> ſayth, <hi>All the Councell cannot erre, the moſt may;</hi> which never yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed) or <hi>Whether two parts</hi> will ſerve (as in the <hi>Tridentine</hi> Synode,) a conſiderable doubt, becauſe, <hi>Nicephorus Calliſtus</hi> relateing the reſolution of a Councell at <hi>Rome</hi> againſt that of <hi>Ariminum</hi> makes them give three reaſons.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Tom: <hi>2,</hi> pag. <hi>172.</hi>
               </note> One <hi>That the Biſhop of Rome, was not preſent.</hi> The ſecond <hi>That moſt did not agree to it.</hi> Thirdly <hi>That others thither gathered were diſpleaſed at their reſolutions:</hi> which proves, that in their opinions, if either <hi>moſt not preſent</hi> agree not to it, or <hi>all preſent</hi> be not pleaſed with it. a <hi>Councell</hi> hath no power to binde. All theſe doubts, I ſay, perſwade me that whatſoever brings with it ſo many <hi>new</hi> que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, can be no fit ender of the <hi>old.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In thoſe things in which,<note place="margin">§ 19.</note> 
               <hi>before</hi> a Generall Councell have <hi>defined,</hi> it is lawfull to hold either way, and damnable to do ſo <hi>after;</hi> I deſire to know how it agreeth with the Charity of the Church, to <hi>define any thing,</hi> and ſo beſtow upon the Divell one path more for us to walke in to him?</p>
            <p>If the <hi>infallibility</hi> of a <hi>Generall Councell</hi> be a point of faith I deſire to know <hi>why</hi> it is ſo?<note place="margin">§ 20.</note> Scripture and Tradition ſeeme to me not to ſay ſo: But if they did, ſo I ſuppoſe you will grant they do of this doctrine, <hi>[That the ſoules of the bleſſed ſhall ſee God before the day of judgement, and not be kept in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Receptacles]</hi> For elſe the doctrine of prayer to Saints can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſtand: and yet for denying this doth <hi>Bellarmine</hi> excuſe Pope <hi>John</hi> 22 (of which beleife they know he was not alone) becauſe the <hi>Church</hi> (he meanes, I doubt not, a Generall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell) had not then condemned it. I deſire to know why ſhould not <hi>he</hi> be condemned as well without one as many <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:108797:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>that are held ſo by their Church, yet condemned by <hi>no Generall Councell?</hi> which if he makes to be the rule of <hi>Hereſie,</hi> it had beene happy to have lived before the Councell of <hi>Nice,</hi> when no opinion had beene damnable but ſome againſt the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles <hi>Councell</hi> at <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> becauſe there had <hi>yet</hi> beene no <hi>Generall</hi> Councell.</p>
            <p>At leaſt, why ſhall not I be excuſed by the ſame reaſon,<note place="margin">§ 21.</note> though I beleive not a <hi>Councell</hi> to be <hi>infallible,</hi> ſince I never heard that any Councell hath decreed that they are <hi>ſo?</hi> Neither, if it have, can we be bound by that Decree, unleſſe made cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſome other way that it ſelfe is ſo.</p>
            <p>If you ſay, we muſt beleive it becauſe of <hi>Tradition;</hi>
               <note place="margin">§ 22.</note> I anſwer <hi>ſometimes</hi> you will have the <hi>not beleiving any thing,</hi> though not declared by a Councell, to have power enough to damne (that is when it makes <hi>againſt us</hi>) at <hi>other times</hi> the <hi>Church</hi> hath not decreed unleſſe a Councell have, and their errour is pardona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and they good Catholiques.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Next,</hi>
               <note place="margin">§ 23.</note> (as I have asked before) how ſhall an <hi>ignorant</hi> man know it? for he, in likely hood, can ſpeake but with a few, from whom he cannot know that <hi>all</hi> of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi>'s part do <hi>now,</hi> and in <hi>paſt</hi> ages have beleeved it to be <hi>Tradition ſo cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely</hi> as to make it a <hi>ground of faith,</hi> (unleſſe he have ſome revelation that thoſe deceive him not.) Neither indeed can thoſe that ſhould enforme him of the opinions of former times be <hi>certainely</hi> enformed themſelves; for truly if (as they would perſwade us) the relation of <hi>Papias</hi> could couſen ſo farre <hi>all</hi> the Prime Doctours of the Chriſtian Church into the beleife of the doctrine of the <hi>Millenaries,</hi> ſo as that <hi>no one</hi> of thoſe two firſt ages oppoſed it, (which appeares plaine enough, becauſe thoſe that after roſe up againſt this opinion, never quoted any for themſelves before <hi>Dionyſius Alexandrinus,</hi> who lived at leaſt two hundred &amp; fifty yeares after Chriſt.) Nay if thoſe firſt men did not only beleeve it as <hi>probable,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dial. cum Tryph p. <hi>307.</hi> lib. <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>33.</hi>
               </note> but <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> layes, <hi>he</hi> holds it, and ſo do <hi>all</hi> that are <hi>in all parts Orthodox</hi> Chriſtians <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naeus</hi> ſets it downe directly for a <hi>Tradition,</hi> and relates the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:108797:6"/>very words that Chriſt uſed when he taught this; (which is plainer then any other <hi>Tradition</hi> is proved, or ſaid to be (out of Antiquity) by them.) If (I ſay) <hi>theſe</hi> could be ſo deceived, why might not <hi>other</hi> of the Ancients as well be by others deceived in other points? And then, what <hi>certainty</hi> ſhall the <hi>Learned</hi> have, when after much labour they thinke they can make it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare that the Ancients thought any thing Tradition, that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it was ſo? And that either the folly, or the knavery of ſome <hi>Papias</hi> deceived them not? I confeſſe it makes me thinke of ſome that <hi>Tully</hi> ſpeakes of, who <hi>(arcem amittunt, dum propug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacula defendunt)</hi> looſe the <hi>fort,</hi> whileſt they defend the <hi>out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>workes;</hi> for whileſt they anſwer this way the arguments of <hi>Tradition</hi> for the opinion of the <hi>Chiliaſts,</hi> they make unuſefull to them the force of <hi>Tradition</hi> to prove any thing elſe by. For which cauſe it was rather wiſely then honeſtly done of them, who before <hi>Feuardentius</hi> ſet him forth, left out that part of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naeus</hi> which we alledge (though we need it not much, for many of the fathers take notice of this beleife of his;) Yet he juſtifies himſelfe for doing it by a worſe blow to them then this it ſelfe, which is, <hi>ſaying,</hi> that <hi>if they leave out all errours in the bookes they publiſh</hi> (that is, I ſuppoſe, all opinions contrary to the Church of <hi>Rome</hi>) <hi>bona pars Scriptorum Patrum Orthodoxorum evaneſceret, a good part of the writings of the Orthodox Fathers muſt vaniſh away.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the <hi>Tradition</hi> that can be found out of Ancients (ſince their witneſſing may deceive us) hath much leſſe ſtrength when they argue only thus:<note place="margin">§ 24.</note> Sure ſo <hi>many</hi> would not ſay this is <hi>true,</hi> and joyne in opinions, if there were no tradition for them. I would have you remember they can deliver their opinion poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly, but either <hi>before</hi> the controverſie ariſe in the Church (up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſome chance) or <hi>after.</hi> If <hi>before,</hi> it is confeſt that they write not <hi>cantiouſly</hi> enough; and ſo they anſwer all they ſeeme to ſay for <hi>Arrius</hi> and <hi>Pelagius</hi> his faith before <hi>themſelves,</hi> and ſo conſequently their <hi>controverſie</hi> (though it may be not their opinion) aroſe. If <hi>after,</hi> then they anſwer often (if any thing be by them at that time ſpoken againſt them) that the <hi>heat of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:108797:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>diſputation</hi> brought it from them, and their reſolution to oppoſe <hi>Heretiques</hi> enough; I deſire it may be lawfull for <hi>us</hi> to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer ſo too, either one of theſe former wayes; or that it is (as often they ſay too) ſome <hi>Hyperbole,</hi> when you preſſe us in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing with the opinions of Fathers. At leaſt, I am ſure if they may deceive us with <hi>ſaying</hi> a thing <hi>is</hi> a <hi>Tradition,</hi> that <hi>is not,</hi> we may be ſooner deceived if we will <hi>ſay</hi> and conclude it for a <hi>Tradition,</hi> when they ſpeake it only as a <hi>Truth,</hi> and (for ought appeares) their <hi>particular Opinion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For beſides, if when <hi>Salvian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">§ 25.</note> comparing the <hi>Arrians</hi> with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill Livers, (and that <hi>after</hi> they were condemned by a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell) extenuates, (by reaſon of their beleiving themſelves in the right) with much inſtance the fault of the <hi>Arrians,</hi> and ſayes, <hi>How they ſhall be puniſht for it in the day of Judgement, none can know but the Judge.</hi> If (I ſay) they confeſſe it to be his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, they muſt alſo confeſſe the doctrine of <hi>their</hi> Church to be different from that of <hi>Salvians</hi> times; becauſe he was allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Member of <hi>that</hi> for all this <hi>ſaying;</hi> whereas he of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> that ſhould ſay ſo of <hi>us</hi> would be accounted <hi>Seſqui-haereticus,</hi> a Heretique and a halfe: Or elſe they muſt <hi>ſay</hi> (which they can onely ſay and not prove) that he was ſo earneſt againſt ill men, that for the aggravation of their crime he leſſened that of the Heretiques; and ſaid, what at another time he would not have ſaid; which if they doe, will it not overthrow wholly the authority of the Fathers? Since we can never <hi>infallibly</hi> know what they thought at <hi>all times,</hi> from what they were moved to <hi>ſay</hi> by ſome <hi>collaterall conſideration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next to this certaine and undoubted <hi>damning</hi> of all out of the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi>
               <note place="margin">§ 26.</note> which averſeth me from it; next comes their putting <hi>all to death,</hi> or at leaſt paines, that do ſo, where they have power: which is an effect, though not a neceſſary one, of the firſt opinion; and that averſeth me yet more; For I doe not beleive <hi>all</hi> to be <hi>damned</hi> whom they damne, but I conceive <hi>all</hi> to be <hi>killed</hi> whom they kill. I am ſure if you looke upon <hi>Conſtantine's</hi> Epiſtle, written to perſwade concord upon the firſt diſagreement between <hi>Alexander</hi> and <hi>Arrius,</hi> you will find
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:108797:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>that <hi>he</hi> thought (&amp; if the Biſhops of his time had at firſt thought <hi>otherwiſe,</hi> he would have beene ſure better informed) that <hi>nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> ſide deſerved either death or damnation. (and yet ſure this queſtion was as great as ever roſe ſince:) For having ſpoken of the opinions as things ſo indifferent, that the Reader might al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt thinke they had beene fallen out at Spurn-point or Ketle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pins, he adds,<note place="margin">Niceph. Tom. <hi>1.</hi> p. <hi>555.</hi>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>For that which is neceſſary is one thing, that all agree and keepe the ſame faith about divine providence.</hi> I am ſure in the ſame Author, <hi>Moſes,</hi> a man praiſed by him, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing to be made Biſhop by <hi>Lucius</hi> becauſe he was an <hi>Arrian,</hi> and he anſwering,<note place="margin">Tom. <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>206.</hi>
               </note> That <hi>he did ill to refuſe it before he knew what his faith was,</hi> Anſwered, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>The baniſhing of Biſhops ſhewes ENOVGH your faith.</hi> So that it is plaine he thought <hi>puniſhing</hi> for opinions to be a marke which might ſerve him to know <hi>falſe</hi> opinions by.</p>
            <p>I beleive throughout Antiquity you will find no putting any to <hi>death,</hi>
               <note place="margin">§ 27.</note> unleſſe it be ſuch as begin to kill firſt, (as the <hi>Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellians</hi> or ſuch like;) I am ſure <hi>Chriſtian Religions</hi> cheife glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry being that it encreaſed by being <hi>perſecuted,</hi> and having that advantage of the <hi>Mahumetan</hi> (which came in by force) me thinkes,<note place="margin">De Regno.</note> (eſpecially ſince <hi>Syneſius</hi> hath told us, and reaſon told men ſo before <hi>Syneſius,</hi> that <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Every thing is deſtroyed by the contrary to what ſetled and compoſed it</hi>) It ſhould be to take ill care of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> to ſeeke to hold it up by <hi>Turkiſh</hi> meanes: at leaſt it muſt breed doubts, that if the Religion had alwaies remained the <hi>ſame,</hi> it would not be defended by wayes ſo <hi>contrary</hi> to thoſe by which it was propagated.</p>
            <p>I deſire recrimination may not be uſed:<note place="margin">§ 28.</note> for though it be true that <hi>Calvin</hi> hath done it, and the Church of <hi>England</hi> a <hi>little,</hi> (which is a little too much) for <hi>Negare manifeſta non audeo, &amp; excuſare immodica non poſſum,</hi> yet She, confeſſing She <hi>may</hi> erre, is not ſo chargeable with any fault as thoſe which pretend they <hi>cannot,</hi> (and ſo will be ſure never to mend it) and beſides, I will be bound to defend no more then I have undertaken, which is,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:108797:7"/>to give reaſons <hi>Why the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>is</hi> fallible.</p>
            <p>I confeſſe this opinion of <hi>damning</hi> ſo many,<note place="margin">§ 29.</note> and this cuſtome of <hi>burning</hi> ſo many, this breeding up thoſe who know nothing elſe in any point of Religion yet to be in readineſſe to cry <hi>To the fire with him,</hi> and <hi>To Hell with him,</hi> (as <hi>Polybius</hi> ſaith in a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine furious faction of an army of ſeverall nations, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently languages, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>All of them underſtood onely this word, Throw at him</hi>) this I ſay in my opinion was it cheifely which made ſo <hi>many</hi> ſo <hi>ſuddainly</hi> leave the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> that indeed to borrow the Authors phraſe, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>—<hi>They needed not perſwaſion to doe it but onely newes that others had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun:</hi> For as this alone if <hi>beleived</hi> makes <hi>all</hi> the reſt be ſo too; So one thing alone <hi>miſliked,</hi> overthrowes alſo <hi>all</hi> the reſt.</p>
            <p>If it were granted that,<note place="margin">§ 30.</note> becauſe it agrees not with the <hi>Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> of God to let men want an <hi>infallible Guide,</hi> therefore there <hi>muſt</hi> be one; and that the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> were that <hi>one;</hi> yet if that teach <hi>any thing,</hi> to my underſtanding, <hi>contrary</hi> to Gods <hi>Goodneſſe,</hi> I am not to receive her doctrine, for the ſame cauſe for which they would have me receive it, (it being <hi>as good</hi> an argument, this <hi>Guide</hi> teaches things contrary to Gods <hi>Goodneſſe, therefore</hi> is not appointed by God; as to ſay, It is agreeable to his <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> there ſhould be a <hi>Guide, therefore</hi> there is one) And ſure it is lawfull to examine <hi>particular</hi> doctrines, whether they agree with that principle which is their <hi>foundation;</hi> and to <hi>that</hi> (me thinkes) to damne him that neither with <hi>negligence</hi> nor <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judication</hi> ſearcheth what is Gods will, though he miſſe of it, is as contrary as the firſt can be ſuppoſed.</p>
            <p>I would know <hi>whether</hi> he that <hi>never heard</hi> of the Church of <hi>Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e</hi> ſhall yet be damned for not beleiving her <hi>infallible.</hi>
               <note place="margin">§ 31.</note> I have ſo good an opinion of them as to aſſure my ſelfe they will anſwer, <hi>he ſhall not.</hi> I will then aske, <hi>Whether</hi> he that hath ſearched what <hi>Religions</hi> there are, and finds <hi>hers</hi> to be one, and <hi>her infallibility</hi> to be part of it, if his reaſon will not aſſent to that, ſhall he be da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for being <hi>inquiſitive</hi> after <hi>truth?</hi> (for he hath committed no other fault greater then the other) &amp; <hi>Whether</hi> ſuch an <hi>ignorance</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:108797:8"/>(I meane after impartiall ſearch) be not of all the other the moſt <hi>invincible?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay grant the <hi>Church</hi> to be <hi>infallible,</hi>
               <note place="margin">§ 32.</note> yet me thinks, he that <hi>denies</hi> it and imployes his reaſon to <hi>ſeeke</hi> if it be true, ſhould be in as good caſe as he that <hi>beleives</hi> it and <hi>ſearcheth not</hi> at all the truth of the propoſition he receives: for I cannot ſee why he ſhould be <hi>ſaved,</hi> becauſe, by reaſon of his <hi>parents</hi> beleiſe, or the Religion of the <hi>Countrey,</hi> or ſome ſuch <hi>accident,</hi> the <hi>truth</hi> was offered to his underſtanding, when had the <hi>contrary</hi> beene offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red he would have received that; and the other damned that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeves <hi>falſhood,</hi> upon as good ground as the other doth <hi>truth;</hi> unleſſe the Church be like a Conjurers circle that will keepe a man from the Devill though he came into it by chance.</p>
            <p>They grant that no man is an <hi>Heretique</hi> that beleeves not his Hereſie <hi>obſtinately;</hi>
               <note place="margin">§ 33.</note> and if he be no Heretique, he may ſure be ſaved. It is not then <hi>certaine damnation</hi> for any man to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the infallibility of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church: but for him only that denies it <hi>obſtinately,</hi> and then I am ſafe; for I am ſure I doe not.</p>
            <p>Neither can they ſay I ſhall be damned for <hi>Schiſme</hi> though not for Hereſie,<note place="margin">§ 34.</note> for he is as well no <hi>Schiſmatique,</hi> though in <hi>Schiſme,</hi> that is <hi>willing</hi> to joyne in communion with the <hi>true</hi> Church, when it appeares to be ſo to him; as he is no <hi>Heretique</hi> though he hold Hereticall opinions, that holds them not <hi>obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately, that is</hi> (as I ſuppoſe) with a deſire to be informed if he be in the wrong.</p>
            <p>Why,<note place="margin">§ 35.</note> if it be not <hi>neceſſary</hi> alwayes to beleeve the <hi>truth,</hi> ſo one beleeve in generall <hi>what the Church would have beleeved,</hi> (for ſo they excuſe great men that have held contrary opinions to theirs now, before they were defined or they knew them to be ſo) why (I ſay) ſhall not the ſame <hi>implicit aſſent</hi> to what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever God would have aſſented to (though I miſtake what it is) be ſufficient? When indeed to beleeve <hi>implicitly</hi> what <hi>God</hi> would have beleeved is to beleeve implicitly likewiſe what the <hi>Church</hi> teacheth, if this doctrine be within the number of <hi>thoſe</hi> which God commands to be beleeved.</p>
            <p>I have therefore the leſſe doubt of this opinion,<note place="margin">§ 36.</note> that I ſhall
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:108797:8"/>have no harme for not beleeving the <hi>infallibility</hi> of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> becauſe of my being ſo farre from <hi>leaning</hi> to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, and ſo ſuffering my <hi>will</hi> to have power over my <hi>under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding,</hi> that if God would leave it to me which Tenet <hi>ſhould</hi> be true, I would rather chooſe that that <hi>ſhould,</hi> then the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. For they may well beleeve me, that I take no pleaſure in tumbling hard and unpleaſant bookes and making my ſelfe giddy with diſputeing of obſcure queſtions and dazled <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.<note place="margin">Caeſariut.</note>
            </p>
            <p>If I could beleeve, there ſhould <hi>alwayes</hi> be (whom I might alwayes <hi>know</hi>) a ſociety of men,<note place="margin">§ 37.</note> whoſe opinions muſt be <hi>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely</hi> true, and who would <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Syneſius.</note> la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to diſcuſſe &amp; define all ariſing doubts, ſo as I might be excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſably at eaſe, &amp; have no part left for me but that of obedience, which muſt needes be a leſſe difficult and ſo a more agreeable way then to endure endleſſe volumes of commentaries, the harſh <hi>Greeke</hi> of <hi>Evagrius,</hi> and the as hard <hi>Latine</hi> of <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> and be pained by diſtinguiſhing betweene different ſenſes and various lections, and he would deſerve not the loweſt place in <hi>Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam</hi> that would preferre theſe ſtudies before ſo many, ſo much more pleaſant, that would rather <hi>imploy</hi> his underſtanding, then <hi>ſubmit it;</hi> and if he could thinke God impoſed upon him only the <hi>reſiſting temptations,</hi> would, by way of addition, require from himſelfe the <hi>reſolving of doubts.</hi> I ſay not that <hi>all theſe bookes</hi> are to be read by <hi>thoſe</hi> who underſtand not the langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, for <hi>them</hi> I conceive their ſeeking into <hi>Scripture</hi> may ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice. But if I have, by Gods grace, skill to looke into them, I cannot better uſe it then in the ſearch of his will, where <hi>they ſay</hi> it is to be found, that I might aſſent to them if there I finde reaſon for it; or if I do not, they may have no excuſe for not excuſing <hi>me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For whereas they ſay,<note place="margin">§ 38.</note> it is <hi>pride</hi> makes <hi>us doubt</hi> of their infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libility; I anſwer that their too much <hi>lazineſſe</hi> and impatience of examining is the cauſe many of <hi>them</hi> do <hi>not doubt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Next,</hi> what <hi>pride</hi> is it, never to aſſent before I find <hi>reaſon</hi> for it, (ſince <hi>they,</hi> when they follow that <hi>Church</hi> as <hi>infallible,</hi>
               <note place="margin">§ 39.</note>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:108797:9"/>
               <hi>pretend reaſon</hi> for it, and will not ſay they would, if they thought they found none) and if they ſay, we do <hi>finde</hi> reaſon but will not <hi>confeſſe</hi> it, then pride hinders not our <hi>aſſent,</hi> but our <hi>declaration</hi> of it; which if it do in any one, he is without queſtion, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>condemned by himſelfe,</hi> and it muſt be a very partiall advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate that would ſtrive to acquit him.</p>
            <p>One much prevailing argument which they make,<note place="margin">§ 40.</note> is this, that whoſoever leave them, fall into <hi>diſſention</hi> betweene them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, whereas <hi>they</hi> in the meane while are alwayes at <hi>unity.</hi> I anſwer, <hi>firſt,</hi> in <hi>this</hi> whereof the queſtion is now, they <hi>all</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. <hi>Secondly,</hi> when there is <hi>fire</hi> for them that <hi>diſagree,</hi> they need not bragge of their uniformity who <hi>conſent. Thirdly they</hi> have many <hi>differences</hi> among them (as <hi>whether</hi> the Pope be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible, <hi>Whether</hi> God predeterminate every action, <hi>Whether</hi> Election and Reprobation depend upon foreſight,) Which ſeeme to me as great as any betweene their adverſaries; and in the <hi>latter</hi> the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> have Ancienter and more generall <hi>Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> on their ſide, then the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath in any other que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion; and as much ground from reaſon for the defence of Gods <hi>goodneſſe,</hi> as they can thinke they have for the neceſſity of an <hi>infallible guide;</hi> yet theſe arguments <hi>muſt not</hi> make the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minicans Heretiques,</hi> and muſt <hi>us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If they ſay,<note place="margin">§ 41.</note> The <hi>Church</hi> hath not <hi>reſolved</hi> it (which ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies only, <hi>that they are not agreed about it,</hi> which is that we ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject) I anſwer, It <hi>ought</hi> to have done, if conformity to the <hi>anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Church</hi> be required, in which <hi>all</hi> that ever I could heare of before Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> (who is very various I confeſſe in it) deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered the contrary to the <hi>Dominicans,</hi> as not doubtfull; and to ſay, it is <hi>lawfull</hi> for them to diſagree whenſoever they <hi>do</hi> not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, is ridiculous: for they cannot do both at once about the ſame point.</p>
            <p>And if they ſay,<note place="margin">§ 42.</note> they meane, by the Churches <hi>not having concluded</hi> it, that a <hi>Councell</hi> hath not, I anſwer that they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne ſome without any, and why not theſe? <hi>Next,</hi> I ſay that the opinion of the <hi>Diffuſed</hi> Church is of more force then the concluſion of a <hi>Repreſentative</hi> (which hath its authority from
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:108797:9"/>the other) and therefore if all extant for foure hundred yeares teach any thing, that is more Hereſie to denie that then any Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non of a Councell.</p>
            <p>But may not howſoever <hi>any</hi> other companie of People (that would maintaine themſelves to be <hi>infallible</hi>) <hi>ſay</hi> as much,<note place="margin">§ 43.</note> that all other ſects differ from one another, and therefore <hi>ſhould</hi> all agree with <hi>them?</hi> Would thoſe not (thinke they) aſcribe all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens diſſentions and learned mens falling into divers He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies to their not allowing <hi>their infallibility</hi> to their not aſſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>their</hi> Decrees? and not ſuffering them <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>to ſit as teachers</hi> of thoſe things that come in queſtion, and to have all others in the place of Diſciples obedient to them? which is that which <hi>Nilus,</hi> a <hi>Greeke</hi> Biſhop, profeſſeth, that becauſe the <hi>Greeks</hi> would not allow the <hi>Romans,</hi> was the only cauſe of ſeperation betweene them.</p>
            <p>They uſe much to object,<note place="margin">§ 44.</note> How <hi>could</hi> errours come into the Church without <hi>oppoſition,</hi> and <hi>mention</hi> both of that oppoſition in hiſtory? I anſwer, they <hi>might</hi> come in not at <hi>once,</hi> but by <hi>degrees;</hi> as in the growth of a childe and the motion of a clock, we ſee neither in the preſent, but know there was a preſent when we finde it paſt. <hi>Next,</hi> ſo many Authours being <hi>loſt,</hi> who can make it <hi>certaine</hi> to me that from none of thoſe, we ſhould have had notice of this <hi>oppoſition,</hi> if they had come to us? <hi>Next</hi> I ſay there are two ſorts of errours, to hold a thing neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry that is <hi>unlawfull</hi> and <hi>falſe,</hi> or that in but <hi>profitable</hi> and <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable:</hi> Of the <hi>ſecond</hi> ſort that errours ſhould come in, it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares not hard to me, and eſpecially in thoſe ages where want of <hi>Printing</hi> made books, and conſequently learning not ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon as now it is; where the few that did ſtudy buſied them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in Schoole-Speculations only, when the Authority of a man of cheife note had a more generall influence then now it hath, and ſo (as <hi>Thucydides</hi> ſaith the Plague did in his time, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the diſeaſe that firſt ſetled in the head <hi>eaſily</hi> paſſed through all the body,) conſidering how apt all men are to deſire that all men
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:108797:10"/>ſhould thinke as they doe, and conſequently to lay a neceſſity upon the receiving that opinion, if they conceived that a way to have it received: And then if it were beleeved <hi>generally profitable,</hi> (as, for example, <hi>Confeſſion,</hi>) who would be apt to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe their calling it <hi>neceſſary,</hi> for the ſame cauſe for which they called it ſo? <hi>Beſides,</hi> if this errour were delivered by ſome Father in the <hi>hot oppoſition</hi> of ſome <hi>Heretique,</hi> it may be none of his ſide would oppoſe it, leaſt they might take advantage by their diſſention, and he that diſputed for the Orthodox ſide, might looſe by it much of his authority.</p>
            <p>The word <hi>[neceſſary]</hi> it ſelfe is often uſed for <hi>very conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent;</hi>
               <note place="margin">§ 45.</note> and then from <hi>neceſſary</hi> in that ſenſe to <hi>abſolutely neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> is no <hi>difficult</hi> change, though it be a <hi>great</hi> one. The Fathers uſe <hi>Heretiques</hi> ſometimes in a large ſenſe, and ſometimes in a ſtricter; &amp; ſo differ in the reckoning them up; Some leaving out thoſe that others put in (though they had ſeene the precedent Catalogue) The doubtfulneſſe of the ſenſe of thoſe words might bring in errour. Names, as an <hi>Altar, Sacrifice, Maſſa,</hi> may have beene uſed firſt in one ſenſe, and the <hi>name</hi> retained though the <hi>thing</hi> ſignified received changes; which may have beene the art of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as it was once of an Emperour of <hi>Rome, Cui proprium fuit nuper reperta</hi> (I leave out <hi>Scelera</hi>) <hi>priſcis verbis obtegere, whoſe property it was to cover things newly found out with ancient tearmes.</hi> And the ſame Author tels us, that the ſame State was as it were cheated out of her liberty becauſe there did remaine, <hi>Eadem Magiſtratuum vocabula, The ſame ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles of Magiſtrates;</hi> and I beleive that if the Proteſtants beyond the Seas would have thought <hi>Biſhops</hi> as good a word as <hi>Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intendents,</hi> (and ſo in other ſuch things) many, who underſtand nothing but <hi>names,</hi> would have miſſed the Scandall they have now taken.</p>
            <p>Theſe waies (I thinke) things may have come,<note place="margin">§ 46.</note> without much <hi>oppoſition,</hi> from being thought <hi>profitable</hi> to be done, and proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to be beleived, to be thought <hi>neceſſary</hi> to be both: and how things <hi>little by little</hi> may have beene received under <hi>old</hi> names, which would not have beene ſo at <hi>once</hi> under <hi>new</hi> ones: (the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:108797:10"/>firſt of theſe being no ſuch ſmall fault but that part of the <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taniſts</hi> hereſie was thinking <hi>uncommanded</hi> faſting daies <hi>neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary</hi> to be obſerved, which without doubt might <hi>lawfully</hi> have beene kept.)</p>
            <p>But my maine anſwer is,<note place="margin">§ 47.</note> that if for an opinion to be in the Church without knowne precedent <hi>oppoſition,</hi> be a <hi>certaine</hi> note of being received from the beginning, let them anſwer, how came in the opinion of the <hi>Chiliaſts</hi> not contradicted till two hundred yeares after it came in.</p>
            <p>To conclude,<note place="margin">§ 48.</note> if they can prove that the Scripture may be a certainer teacher of truths to <hi>them</hi> then to <hi>us,</hi> ſo <hi>they</hi> may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the <hi>infallibility</hi> of the Church out of it, and <hi>we</hi> nothing; If they can prove the Churches <hi>infallibility</hi> to be a ſufficient <hi>Guide</hi> for him that <hi>doubts</hi> Which is the Church, and cannot <hi>examine</hi> that (for want of learning) by her cheife marke, which is <hi>confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity</hi> with the Ancient; If they can prove that the <hi>conſent of Fathers</hi> long together (if they had it) is a ſtronger argument a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>us,</hi> then againſt the <hi>Dominicans;</hi> If they can prove that though the firſt of them affirme that ſuch a thing is <hi>Tradition,</hi> and beleived by all Chriſtians (and this aſſertion till a great while after uncontradicted) yet <hi>they are not</hi> bound to receive it, and, upon leſſe grounds, <hi>we are;</hi> If indeed <hi>any</hi> can prove by <hi>any infallible way</hi> the infallibility of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> &amp; the neceſſity under paine of damnation for all men to beleive it, (which were the more ſtrange, becauſe <hi>Iuſtin Martyr,</hi> and <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens Alexandrinus</hi> among the Ancients, and <hi>Eraſmus</hi> and <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dovicus Vives</hi> among the modernes, beleive ſome Pagans to be ſaved) I will ſubſcribe to it, And</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.<note place="margin">Sophoc.</note>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>If any man ſhall vouchſafe to thinke either <hi>this,</hi>
               <note place="margin">§ 49.</note> or the Author of it, of value enough to confute the <hi>one</hi> and enforme the <hi>other,</hi> I ſhall deſire him to doe it with proceeding to the buſineſſe, and not ſtanding upon any ſmall ſlip of mine, (of which ſort this may be full) and with that Civility which is fit to be uſed by men that are not ſo paſſionate as to have the definition of reaſonable
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:108797:11"/>creatures in vain; (remembring that <hi>truth</hi> in likelihood, is where her Author <hi>God</hi> was, in the <hi>ſtill voice,</hi> and not in the <hi>loud wind;</hi> And that <hi>Epiphanius</hi> excuſeth himſelfe if he have called any He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retiques in his anger, <hi>Deceivers,</hi> or <hi>Wretches,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and I requeſt him alſo to bring me to the <hi>Truth</hi> (if I be out of it) not onely by his <hi>arguments</hi> but alſo by his <hi>prayers:</hi> which waies if <hi>he</hi> uſe, and <hi>I</hi> ſtill continue on the part I am of, and yet doe neither <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, nor <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, neither am wilfully blind, nor deny impudently what I ſee, then I am confident that neither <hi>he</hi> will have reaſon to be offended with me in this world, nor <hi>God</hi> in the <hi>next.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>FALKLAND.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:108797:11"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
